Guide to the Bruno de Finetti Papers, 1924-2000 ASP.1992.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Research, 1927-2000; III.
  - Writings and Teachings in Economics, 1930-1978; 5.
    - "Principi e metodi delle scelte economiche:" Talk by de Finetti at a URPT Conference (Unione regionale province Toscane) in Florence, on Principles of Economic Choices, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - "Ciclo Urbino 72", 1972-1973 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - CIME Utopia: De Finetti's lectures at CIME (Centro internazionale matematico estivo) between 1972 and 1977, 1971-1977 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - CIME Summer Sessions on Mathematical Economics, Econometrics, and Statistical Methods and Inference, 1965-1975 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - CIME Summer Classes: Various Notes and Correspondence, 1930, 1974-1978 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Course on Operational Research at the Istituto superiore per la direzione aziendale, 1958 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Università internazionale per gli studi sociali, Rome, 1958-1961 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - "Politica delle valute e assicurazioni:" Seminars sponsored by the IBM World Trade European Education Centre in Blaricum, Netherlands, and La Tour de Peilz, Switzerland, 1961-1963 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Lecture by Guido Carli at the Istituto Superiore di Studi Economici "A. Olivetti", Ancona, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1934-2000; IV.
  Series IV Includes family and personal correspondence and numerous exchanges covering de Finetti's professional and academic activities. Some of the interactions are with institutions or individuals representing institutions. Topics discussed include research by de Finetti and others, mutual exchange of papers and related comments, and de Finetti's publications and teaching projects. Folders 1-3 cover mostly personal and family matters. Folders 7 and 8 were created by de Finetti and their original order was preserved. Some of the topics discussed in folder 7 are family matters, de Finetti's activities as a visiting professor at the University of Chicago, and Savage's visit to Italy. Included is correspondence with Jimmie Savage, Jerzy Neyman, Dario Fürst, and correspondence between Savage and Karl Popper. Folder 8 contains exchanges between de Finetti and Dennis Lindley, Alexandre Marc, and Camillo Dagum. All subsequent folders are arranged alphabetically by correspondent and then chronologically within folders.
  - Offprint Alcune Lettere Giovanili de B. de Finetti alla Madre, 2000 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence with Gino Errico, Brother in Law, 1934-1952 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Family and Personal Correspondence and Notes, 1948-1984 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Unidentified Correspondents, 1935-1978 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Thank-You Notes, 1961-1964 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Letters to Newspapers and Institutions and Petitions, 1966-1974 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Compiled by de Finetti, 1956-1976 (Box 10, Folder 7-8)
  - A-B, 1936-1985 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - C, 1944-1981 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - D, 1946-1978 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - E-G, 1937-1984 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - H-L, 1949-1981 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - M, 1946-1982 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - N-P, 1947-1984 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - R-S, 1946-1985 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - T-Z, 1946-1980 (Box 10, Folder 17)
- Theory of Teaching and School Reform, 1957-1981; V.
  Series V covers two areas in which de Finetti showed great personal interest and involvement, and which extend beyond his professional activities. One of them is his interest in the theory of teaching, its application, and its improvement. The second area documents de Finetti's political and social activism and ensuing legal issues. Both areas are divided into two subseries. The first subseries is entitled Theory of Teaching and School Reform and contains typescripts, newspaper clippings, journal issues, and correspondence that illustrate de Finetti's efforts to improve science and mathematics teaching, teacher education, and school curricula. Subjects discussed are de Finetti such as Il "saper vedere" in matematica and Perchè la matematica?, de Finetti's plans for educational movies, and a project for an educational center for teachers. The second subseries is comprised under Socio-Political and Juridical Issues and holds letters, memoranda, newspaper clippings, articles, and court records. Documented are his membership in the facist party, his participation in the Movimento Politico Lavoratori (MPL), and his role as editor of the Radical Party's publication Notizie Radicali.
  - Theory of Teaching and School Reform, 1957-1981; 1.
    - "Mat. Log. Int. e corrisp. Didattica ecc.", 1957-1958 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - "Zanichelli", 1963-1964 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - "Saper vedere", 1965-1967 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - "Per Ing. Max", 1970-1974 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - "Regione Emilia Romagna", 1972 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - "PKM" (Draft of an Introduction to de Finetti's Perchè la matematica?), 1972 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - "CIME", 1973-1978 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - UMI-Ingegneria: Survey by Unione matematici italiani on mathematics curricula, 1976-1977 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Program for Teaching Methodology at the University of Rome, no date (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Material on Teaching Methodology and Mathematics Teaching, 1957-1980 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - "Insegnamento di materie scientifiche nella scuola media unica e preparazione degli insegnanti", 1963 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - "Apunti di Lombardo Radice", 1963-1966 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Mathematics Curricula in Economics and Political Economy in High Schools, no date (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - "Centro Europeo dell'educazione", 1971-1972 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - "Corona Cinematografica", 1970-1974 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Science and Mathematics Teaching in Secondary Schools, 1966-1977 (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - "Corso Aggiornamento 1964: Compl. Di Matematica." (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - "Frascati IUCTS 1963" (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - "Mathesis", 1972-1981 (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - Mathesis 2, 1966-1974 (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - Mathematical Contest in Rome and Mathematics Olympiad in Moscow, 1962-1968 (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - Socio-Political and Juridical Issues, 1934-1985; 2.
    - U.S. Politics and Culture, 1958 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - "DLS-65", 1964-1965 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - "Antiimbecillite", 1965 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - "Ist. Matem. Castelnuovo", 1970-1972 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - "MPL", 1971-1974 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Overpopulation and Sustainable Development, 1972 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - "Giornali; Mandato di Cattura 1977", 1972-1981 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - "Ambasciata Americana", 1977-1978 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Political Notes, 1964-1978 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Political Articles and Newsletters, 1971-1985 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - "Sociologia.", 1942-1945 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Material on "Burofrenia", 1952-1963 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - "Questionario Min. Costituente - 'Epurazione'.", 1945-1948 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Christianity and the Catholic Church, 1965-1982 (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1934-1985 (Box 12, Folder 15)
- Writings by de Finetti and Others, 1955-1985; VI.
  Series VI comprises writings by de Finetti and others in form of offprints, typescripts, newspaper and magazine clippings. Some articles were compiled by de Finetti himself and some were apparently sent to him by others, as included correspondence shows. Headings in quotation marks indicate that the respective folder was originally created by de Finetti.
  - "Probabilità scritti recenti vari AA", 1981-1984 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - "Gillies Lakatos", 1963-1964, 1972-1973 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - "Lombardini economia", 1980 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - "Fréchet-psicol-econometrica", 1955 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Maurice Allais, 1956-1957 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Haynes Phillips, 1972, 1974 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Nathan Stemmer, 1971-1972 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Ole Hagen, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Mary A. B. Brazier, 1975 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - R.L. Hudson and G.R. Moody, 1974-1975 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Karl Borch, 1968-1976 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Alfonso D'Errico, 1974-1975 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Ian Hacking, 1966 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Luigi Spaventa and Stefano Rodotà, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Beniamino Segre and Giovanni Sansone, 1975 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Roberta Ferronato, 1980 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Edward J. Nell, 1967 (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Jacob Marschak, 1964, 1974 (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - Yakar Kannai, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - Ragnar Frisch, 1965 (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - Giandomenico Majone, 1974 (Box 13, Folder 21)
  - E.J. Misshan, 1976 (Box 13, Folder 22)
  - Bruno de Finetti, 1956-1978 (Box 13, Folder 23)
  - Goffredo Pacioni, 1964 (Box 13, Folder 24)
  - Giuliano Marini, 1962 (Box 13, Folder 25)
  - Luigi Gedda, 1965 (Box 13, Folder 26)
  - Reinhardt Viertl, 1984-1985 (Box 13, Folder 27)
  - Abner Shimony, no date (Box 13, Folder 28)
  - I. John Good and R.A. Gaskins, 1972 (Box 13, Folder 29)
  - Arlo D. Hendrickson and Robert J. Buehler, University of Minnesota School of Statistics, 1970, 1974 (Box 13, Folder 30)
  - J. Tiago de Oliveira, 1974 (Box 13, Folder 31)
  - P.R. Freeman, 1970 (Box 13, Folder 32)
  - A. Kolmogoroff, no date (Box 13, Folder 33)
  - Dennis V. Lindley, no date (Box 13, Folder 34)
  - Robert L. Winkler, 1967 (Box 13, Folder 35)
  - Romano Scozzafava, 1984 (Box 13, Folder 36)
  - Freda Conway, 1970 (Box 13, Folder 37)
  - P.M. Williams, 19870 (Box 13, Folder 38)
  - Carla Rossi, 1976 (Box 13, Folder 39)
  - Joseph B. Kadane, 1984 (Box 13, Folder 40)
  - Pierfrancesco Periti, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 41)
  - Bruce Hill, no date (Box 13, Folder 42)
  - Michael Goldstein, 1981-1984 (Box 13, Folder 43)
  - Vittorio Grilli, 1984 (Box 13, Folder 44)
  - I.J. Jordaan, no date (Box 13, Folder 45)
  - Mario Di Bacco, no date (Box 13, Folder 46)
  - Godehard Link, no date (Box 13, Folder 47)
  - A.P. Dawid, 1970, 1982 (Box 13, Folder 48)
  - S.N. Afriat, E.S. Pearson, Pasquale Saraceno, and István Vincze, 1963-1984 (Box 13, Folder 49)
  - Sylos-Labini, Paolo. "Appunti di economia," Typescript, 1964-1965 (Box 13, Folder 50)
  - Unidentified Authors, 1966 (Box 13, Folder 51)
  - Issues of Journals and Newsletters, 1960-1983 (Box 13, Folder 52)
  - Notes Found in Books from de Finetti's Library, 1962-1990 (Box 13, Folder 53)
  - Pamphlet for the "Cerimonia in omaggio a Bruno de Finetti", July 20th, 2005 (Box 13, Folder 54)
- Books of de Finetti's Library, VII.
  This series contains books annotated by de Finetti.
  - Albèrgamo, Francesco. Principi della Conoscenza Umana. Classici di Filosofia e Pedagogia Collezione Diretta da Michele Lecce, 26. "La Scaligera,, Verona: Casa Editrice, Vicolo Chiodo, 8, 1942. Annotated. (Box 14)
  - Anile, Antonio. Questo è l'Uomo. Firenze: Stab. Grafici A. Vallecchi, 1943. Annotated.
  - Bertacchi, Giovanni. Voci dal Mondo: Antologia della Lingua Italiana per le Scuole Medie Inferiori. Torino: Stamperia Reale G. B. Paravia e Comp. Annotated.
  - Bollettino Bimestrale del Centro Didattico Nazionale per l'Istruzione Tecnica e Professionale. Anno 6, 1972, N. 6 Novembre-Dicembre. Annotated.
  - Boringhieri, Cora Diamond. Lezioni di Wittgenstein sui Fondameni della Matematica. Novalito di Torino, 1982. Annotated.
  - Bourbaki, N. Théorie des Ensembles: Les Stuctures Fondamentales de L'Analyse, Livre I. Paris: Hermann, & Cie, Éditeurs, 1939. Annotated.
  - Caravale, G. La Crisi delle Teorie Economiche. Seminari di Economia Vol.N. 1 Collana dell'Istituto di Economia Facoltà di Economia e Commercio di Perugui. Franco Angeli Editore, 2000. Annotated.
  - Castelnuovo, Emma. I Numeri: Aritmetica Pratica. Firenze: "La Nuova Italia" Editrice, 1962. Annotated.
  - Catalano, Giorgio and Lombardo-Radice, Lucio. Minialgebra. Milano: Giangiacomo Feltrinelli Editore, 1972. Annotated.
  - Cattaneo, Carlo. Lombardia Antica e Moderna. Firenze: G. C. Sansoni Editore, 1943. Annotated.
  - Cavallucci, Guido. L'Intelligenza Come Forza Rivoluzionaria. Tivoli: Biblioteca del Secolo Fascista, 1935. Annotated.
  - Chesterson, G.K. L'Ortodossia. Brescia: Morcelliana, 1926. Annotated.
  - Cohen, John. Caso Abilità e Fortuna in Psicologia: Psicologia della probabilità. Editrice Universitaria, 1960. Annotated.
  - Dardi, Dino. Idee: Raggiunte e da Raggiungere, per Superare. Milano: Edizioni Corbaccio, 1934. Annotated.
  - Requisiti per un Sistema Economico Accettabile in Relazione alle Esigenze della Collettivita'. Franco Angeli Editore, Milano, 1971. Annotated.
  - Matematica Logico Intuitiva: Nozioni di Matematiche Complementari e di Calcolo Differenziale e Integrale Come Introduzione Agli Studi di Scienze Economiche Statistiche Attuariali. Società Poligrafica Editoriale, Castello, 1959. Annotated.
  - Evoluzione Biologica e I Grandi Problemi della Biologia: L'Addomesticazione degli Animali e delle Piante (1983: Roma, Italia). Contributi del Centro Linceo Interdisciplinare di Scienze Matematiche e Loro Applicazioni, N. 68. Roma: Accademia Nazionale dei Lincei, 1984. Annotated.
  - Faggin, Giuseppe. Antologia. Classici di Filosofia e Pedagogia Collezione Diretta da Michele Lecce, 24. "La Scaligera,, Casa Editrice, Verona, Vicolo Chiodo, 8, 1941. Annotated.
  - Forecasting on a Scientific Basis; Proceedings. International Summer Institute on Foresting on a Scientific Basis (1966: Curia, Portugal). Lisboa: Centro de Economia e Finanças, 1967. Annotated.
  - Grayson, C. Jackson, Jr. Decisions Under Uncertainty: Drilling Decisions by Oil and Gas Operators. Norwood, MA: Plimpton Press, 1960. Annotated.
  - Küng, Hans. Incarnazione di Dio: Introduzione al Pensiero Teologico di Hegel, Prolegomeni ad una Futura Cristologia. Queriniana, Brescia, 1972. Signed by author. Annotated.
  - Lettera a una Professoressa. Scuola di Barbiana: Libreria Editrice Fiorentina, 1967. Annotated.
  - Levy, Paul. Quelues Aspects de la Pensée d'un Mathématicien. Librairie Scientifique et Technique Albert Blanchard, Paris, 1970. Signed by Author. Annotated.
  - Lindley, D.V. Making Decisions. Great Britain: John Wiley & Sons, Ltd., 1971. Annotated.
  - Nietzsche, Federico. Aurora. Milano: Casa Editrice Sociale, 1925. Annotated.
  - Orestano, Francesco. Verità Dimostrate: Saggi di Filosofia Critica. Napoli: Casa Editrice Rondinella Alfredo, 1934. Annotated.
  - Padoa-Schioppa, F. e T. Agenda e Non-Agenda: Limiti e crisi della politica economica. Banca Commerciale Italiana, Milano, 1984. Annotated.
  - Palomba, Giuseppe. La distribuzione social del Reddito Nazionale. De Simone Editore, Napoli, 1984. Annotated.
  - Pirou, G., Somart, W., Durbin, E.F.M., Patterson, E. M., and Spirito, U. Capitalismo e Corporativismo di Ugo Spirito. Firenze: G.C. Sansoni, 1933. Annotated.
  - La Crisi del Capitalismo. Traduzioni di S. La Colla. Terza edizione. G. C. Sansoni Editore, Firenze, 1934. Annotated.
  - Polya, George. La Scoperta Matematica, Capire, Imparare e Insegnare a Risolvere i Problemi, Volume I. Giangiacomo Feltrinelli Editore, Milano, 1971. Annotated.
  - La Scoperta Matematica, Capire, Imparare e Insegnare a Risolvere i Problemi, Volume II. Giangiacomo Feltrinelli Editore, Milano, 1970. Annotated.
  - "Proposte per il Nuovo Piano della Scuola." Ministerio della Pubblica Istruzione: Comitato Tecnico per la Programmazione. Roma: Istituto Poligrafico Dello Stato, 1971. Annotated.
  - Roncaglia, Alessandro. Keynes: A un secolo dalla nascita. Banca Popolare dell' Etruria/Studi e Ricerche, 1984. Annotated.
  - Rosenberg, Arturo. Storia del Bolscevismo da Marx al Nostri Giorni. Firenze, G. C. Sansoni, Editore, 1933. Annotated.
  - Rovero, Giuseppe. Tre Dialoghi Tra Hylas e Philonous. Classici di Filosofia e Pedagogia Collezione Diretta da Michele Lecce, 31. "La Scaligera,, Casa Editrice, Verona, Vicolo Chiodo, 8, 1942. Annotated.
  - Schilpp, Paul Arthur. Albert Einstein, Scienziato e filosofo: Autobiografia de Einstein e Saggi di Vari Autori. Boringhieri, Torino, 1958. Annotated.
  - Tilgher, Adriano. Relativisti Contemporanei. Roma: Libreria di Schienze e Lettere, Piazza Madama, 1923. Annotated.
  - Filosofia delle Morali: Studio Sulle Forze, Le Forme, gli Stili della Vita Morale. Roma: Dott. G. Bardi, 1937. Annotated.
  - Il Caso. Estratto dalla Rivista "Religio,, Roma, 1939. Signed by author. Annotated.
  - Von Beckerath, E., Cole, G.D.H., Lorwin, L.L., Dobbert, G., Conliffe, J.B., Nagao, S., Spiritu, U. Nuove Esperienze Economiche. Firenze, G. C. Sansoni, Editore, 1935. Annotated.
  - The Writings of Leonard Jimmie Savage. American Statistical Association and the Institute of Mathematical Statistics. 1980. Annotated.
- Multimedia, 1979; VIII.
  Related Materials
  Published versions of these lectures may be found in De Finetti, Bruno. Philosophical Lectures on Probability. Collected, edited, and annotated by Alberto Mura. Translated by Hykel Hosni. Introductory essay by Maria Carla Galavotti. Springer, 2008. This is a revised version of an earlier publication, Filosofia della probabilita. Milan: Il Saggiatore, 1995.
  - Lesson 1: March 13, 1979, First Part and Second Part, 1979-03-13 (Box 15, Cassette 1)
  - Lesson 2: March 14, 1979 First and Second Part, 1979-03-14 (Box 15, Cassette 2)
  - Lesson 4: March 20, 1979; Lesson 6: March 22, 1979, First Part of Three, 1979-03-20 (Box 15, Cassette 3)
  - Lesson 6: March 22, 1979, Second and Third Part of Three, 1979-03-22 (Box 15, Cassette 4)
  - Lesson 7: March 27, 1979, First and Second Part, 1979-03-27 (Box 15, Cassette 5)
  - Lesson 8: March 28, 1979, First and Second Part, 1979-03-28 (Box 15, Cassette 6)
  - Lesson 9: March 29, 1979, 1979-03-29 (Box 15, Cassette 7)
  - Lesson 10:April 3, 1979, First and Second Part, 1979-04-03 (Box 15, Cassette 8)
  - Lesson 11: April 4, 1979, First and Second Part, 1979-04-04 (Box 15, Cassette 9)
  - Lesson 12: April 5, 1979, First and Second Part, 1979-04-05 (Box 15, Cassette 10)
  - Lesson 13: April 27, 1979, 1979-04-13 (Box 15, Cassette 11)
  - Lesson 14: May 2, 1979, First and Second Part, 1979-05-02 (Box 15, Cassette 12)
  - Lesson 15: May 3, 1979, First and Second Part, 1979-05-03 (Box 15, Cassette 13)
  - Lesson 16: May 4, 1979, First and Second Part, 1979-05-04 (Box 15, Cassette 14)
  - Lesson 17: May 8, 1979, First and Second Part, 1979-05-08 (Box 15, Cassette 15)
  - Lesson 18: May 9, 1979, First and Second Part, 1979-05-09 (Box 15, Cassette 16)
    Physical Characteristics
    Note: Low quality is in the master tape
  - Lesson 20: May 15, 1979, First and Second Part, 1979-05-15 (Box 15, Cassette 17)
  - Lesson 21: May 16, 1979, First and Second Part, 1979-05-16 (Box 15, Cassette 18)
  - Lesson 22: May 17, 1979, 1979-05-17 (Box 15, Cassette 19)